<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Food Processing | Alberto Tonda</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/food-processing/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/food-processing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Food Processing</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/icon_hu13064559619334802728.png</url>
      <title>Food Processing</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/food-processing/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>AI in food processing</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/research/food-processing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/research/food-processing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Starting with my first post-doctoral position, I applied computational intelligence techniques to the field of food processing, a domain where the limited amount of data and the abundance of expert knowledge pose interesting challenges to ML and AI algorithms. This activity later became the main focus of my career as a permanent researcher at INRA/INRAE. The case studies I tackled, carried out mainly in the scope of the co-supervisions of PhD students Etienne Descamps and Thomas Chabin, include modeling diary emulsions 
, 
,
freeze-drying of lactic acid bacteria 
, 
, 
,
biscuit cooking 
,
cleaning processes of industrial machines 
, 
,
behavior of the pepsin enzyme 
, 
, 
,
ecosystem services 
. I later chaired the European COST Action CA15118 &lt;em&gt;Mathematical and Computer Science Methods for Food Science and Industry&lt;/em&gt; (2016-2020), a networking project that gathered experts from both academia and industry, to make a point on the state of the art and the possible future trajectories of the sector. The project led to several reviews and position papers 
, 
, 
, 
. As an expert of the domain, I have been involved in several other internal INRAE activities that also led to position papers 
, 
, 
, 
, 
, 
, and I have provided my perspective in two invited talks at Academie de Technologies (Paris, France) and at the University of Sarajevo (Bosnia-Herzegovina).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
