<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog | Alberto Tonda</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/icon_hu13064559619334802728.png</url>
      <title>Blog</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Invited talk on program synthesis</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/2024-11-25-irisa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/2024-11-25-irisa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The CNRS 
 (Institute of Research on Computer Science and Random Systems, IRISA) in Rennes, France, invited me to give a talk with the aim of establishing a contact between different communities working on program synthesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract-of-the-talk&#34;&gt;Abstract of the talk&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evolutionary algorithms (EAs) are stochastic optimization techniques, designed to tackle objective functions for which other techniques fail (for example, due to the impossibility of computing derivatives, non-convexity of the function landscape, or sheer size of the search space). Genetic programming (GP) is a technique belonging to the field of EAs, designed to stochastically explore search spaces of complex structures, for example trees or graphs. Since these structures can be used to represent computer programs, GP has been successfully applied to the task of program synthesis since the early 2000s, automatically generating computer programs for specific applications. In this talk, I will briefly introduce EAs and GP, before going over the current state of the art in EA-based program synthesis, focusing in particular on strengths, limitations, and possible ways forward.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visiting Victoria University, NZ</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/2024-06-24-vuw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/2024-06-24-vuw/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During the 2024 summer I spent almost two months visiting the researchers and students at the 
 of 
, New Zealand. Prof. Mengjie Zhang and his colleagues warmly welcomed me in spite of the relatively cold weather of the austral hemisphere, and we had a excellent exchange of ideas; not to mention, I had the opportunity of working again with the brilliant Ph.D. student Hengzhe Zhang, with whom I previously collaborated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks again to Prof. Mengjie Zhang and all his colleagues (Bing Xue, Xiaoying Gao, Fangfang Zhang, Hui Ma, and many others I am surely forgetting) for inviting me and for the warm welcome!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Silver medal at the HUMIES awards</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/2022-07-13-gecco-humies/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/2022-07-13-gecco-humies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On July 13th, 2022, I had the pleasure of receiving the Silver Medal at the HUMIES (
) held in Boston, MA, USA. The prize was awarded for a human-competitive result obtained using evolutionary computation. My collaborators and I (Eric Claassen, Etienne Coz, Johan Garssen, Aletta D. Kraneveld, Alejandro Lopez Rincon, Lucero Mendoza Maldonado, Carmina A. Perez Romero, Patrick Tabeling, Jessica Vanhomwegen) worked on the automatic discovery of primers for virus, with a specific application to COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Invited talk at ENCALS 2022</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/2022-06-03-encals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/2022-06-03-encals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On June 3rd, 2022, I had the pleasure of giving an invited talk at the first Non-Coding RNA in Motor Neuron Diseases (MND) and Amyothropic Lateral Sclerosis (ALS) International Symposium, a side event of the 
 in Edinburgh, Scotland, UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The subject of my talk was feature selection of microRNA biomarkers to help machine learning robustly classifying diseases. The application I presented is cancer classification, based on a 2020 work in cooperation with Alejandro Lopez-Rincon and several other authors&lt;!-- [2020 work in cooperation with Alejandro Lopez-Rincon and several other authors](/publication/lopezrincon-2020-machine/)--&gt;. The technique proposed in the study, Recursive Ensemble Feature Selection, can in principle be applied to datasets from other diseases, and during the symposium we discussed the possibility of applying it to an ALS dataset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank all the ENCALS organizing committee, and in particular 
, for the kind invite and the productive interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
